中文翻譯 @SaltyEggPain
Bluray版字幕  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第三集
我們的身世很神秘
We were born into a mystery
這一直困擾著我們
one that has haunted us
自從人類誕生就是如此
since at least as long as we've been human.
在這個星空覆蓋下的小星球上
We awakened on this tiny world
我們開始有了意識
beneath a blanket of stars,
就如同被遺棄在門口的嬰兒
like an abandoned baby left on a doorstep
沒有留下隻字片語
without a note to explain
告訴我們是誰 我們從哪裏來
where we came from, who we are,
我們的世界會是怎樣
how our universe came to be.
我們在宇宙中是否還有其他同類
And with no idea how to end our cosmic isolation.
我們必須自己找出答案
We've had to figure it all out for ourselves.
我們最大的財富
Best thing we had going for us
就是我們的智慧
was our intelligence,
特別是識別規律的天賦
especially our gift for pattern recognition,
經過遠古以來進化過程的改造
sharpened over eons of evolution.
那些擅長區分獵物和猛獸的人
The ones who were good at spotting prey and predator,
擅長識別有毒的食物的人
telling poisonous plants from the nourishing ones,
他們活下去並繁衍的幾率更大
they had a better chance to live and reproduce.
他們倖存下來 並把識別規律的基因傳下去
They survived and passed on those genes for pattern recognition
優勢顯而易見
with its obvious advantages.
地球上的不同文化
Cultures all over the planet
都是仰望同一個星空
looked up at the same stars
然後做出不同的解讀
and found different pictures there.
我們用這種天賦在自然界中尋找規律
We used this gift for recognizing patterns in nature
解讀天空中的年歷
to read the calendar in the sky.
寫在星空中的信息
The messages written in the stars
告訴我們的祖先
told our forefathers and mothers
何時安營  何時啟程
when to camp and when to move on.
獸群何時遷徙
When the migratory herds
何時下雨  何時天寒
and when the rains and the cold would come.
何時他們可以停下來休息
And when they would cease for a time.
當他們觀察恆星間的運動與地球上
When they observed the direct connection between the motions of the stars
生命週期變化之間的直接聯繫
and the seasonal cycles of life on Earth,
他們很自然地得出結論
they concluded, naturally,
天上發生的變化
that what happens up there
必然和地球上發生的事情息息相關
must be directed at us down here.
也有道理 對吧
It makes sense, right?
如果把天空看成日曆
If the sky was a calendar
有人在上面貼上一張便簽紙
and somebody stuck a Post-it note on top of it,
除了傳達信息還會是什麼
what else could it be but a message?
所以  當天空的秩序被突然打破時
And so, when the heavenly order was suddenly violated
比如 當彗星劃過天際時
by the apparition of a comet in the sky...
人們就會和自身聯繫起來
they took it personally.
也不能怪他們
Can we really blame them?
那時 對於所發生的事情也沒有其他
Back then, they had no other logical explanation
符合邏輯的解釋
for what was happening.
那是很久以前
This was long before
沒人會認為地球是個
anyone had yet to imagine Earth
傾斜自轉的行星
as a spinning planet with a tilted axis,
繞著太陽公轉
revolving around the Sun.
每種文化中的古人都犯過相同的錯誤
Every ancient human culture made the same mistake,
彗星一定是來自眾神
a comet must be a message,
或某一個神的旨意
sent by the gods... or one particular god.
幾乎是必然的  我們的祖先認為
And almost invariably, our ancestors concluded
大事不妙
the news was not good.
不論你是古阿茲特克人
It didn't matter if you were an ancient Aztec,
古英國人 古巴比倫人  古印度人
Anglo-Saxon, Babylonian, Hindu.
彗星都是毀滅的前兆
Comets were portents of doom.
僅有的不同是
The only difference among them
災難預報的精確程度
was the precise nature of the coming disaster.
災禍 源自希臘語中的 災星
"Dis-aster," as in the Greek word for "bad star."
對東非的馬塞人來說
To the Masai of East Africa,
彗星意味著饑荒
a comet meant famine.
對南非的祖魯人來說
To the Zulu in the south,
意味著戰爭
it meant war.
對於西非的迦納人來說
To the Eghap people of the west,
意味著瘟疫
it meant disease.
對薩伊人來說
To the Djaga of Zaire,
薩伊人（剛果）
特指 天花
specifically "smallpox."
對於他們的鄰居 陸巴人
To their neighbors, the Luba,
彗星預示著領袖之死
a comet foretold the death of a leader.
古代中國人有著驚人的系統分類
The ancient Chinese were remarkably systematic.
大約公元前1400年
Starting in roughly 1400 BC,
他們就開始了對彗星的
they began recording and cataloguing
記錄和分類
the apparitions of comets.
三尾彗星
A three-tailed comet
意味著國家的災難
meant calamity for the state.
四尾彗星
A four-tailed comet
標誌著瘟疫降臨
signified an epidemic was coming.
人類識別規律的天賦
The human talent for pattern recognition
是把雙刃劍
is a two-edged sword.
我們尤其擅長尋找規律
We're especially good at finding patterns,
哪怕無中生有
even when they aren't really there--
或者 牽強附會
something known as "false pattern recognition."
我們渴望證明
We hunger for significance,
人類的存在對這個宇宙
for signs that our personal existence
有著重大的意義
is of special meaning to the universe.
說到底 我們的渴望
To that end, we're all too eager
使我們寧願相信
to deceive ourselves and others,
烤麵包上出現的聖像
to discern a sacred image in a grilled cheese sandwich
或者彗星帶著上帝的旨意
or find a divine warning in a comet.
今天 我們已經
Today, we know exactly where comets come from
清楚知道了彗星的本質
and what they're made of.
我們的想像之舟
Our Ship of the Imagination,
由科學和好奇共同驅動
fueled by equal parts of science and wonder,
可以帶我們遊歷任何時空
can take us anywhere in space and time.
可以走的比光速還快
It can travel faster than light
可以呈現肉眼無法看見的事物
and render visible those things that cannot be seen.
將我們進入一條神秘的溪流
It's carrying us to a mysterious realm
距離太陽一光年的地方
that lies one light-year from the Sun.
眾多的星體為何聚集
What is this swarm of worlds?
是由外星生物安排的嗎
Was it organized by alien beings?
不是
No.
萬有引力而已
Just gravity.
歷年的積雪
These are the snows of yesteryear,
山峰般的寒冰和岩石
drifting mountains of ice and rock,
太陽系誕生時的剩餘產物
the preserved remnants of the birth of the solar system.
組成了 奧爾特雲團
It's called the Oort Cloud,
以荷蘭天文學家奧爾特命名
after Jan Oort, the Dutch astronomer
他在1950年就預言了這個雲團的存在
who foretold its existence back in 1950.
他原本想解決一個悖論
He was trying to solve a paradox.
彗星有很多種消亡的方式
There's so many ways for comets to die.
因為他們會穿過行星的軌道
Because they cross the orbits of planets,
經常發生碰撞
comets frequently collide with them.
彗星很大程度上由冰組成
Comets are largely made of ice,
所以 每次接近太陽時
so every time they come near the Sun,
他們會蒸發掉一部分
they lose a part of themselves through evaporation.
這個過程重複幾千次
And after several thousand trips,
所有的冰 蒸發了
their ice is all gone,
殘餘的彗星就是現在的小行星
and what remains of the comet is now an asteroid.
彗星被太陽系的引力場排斥
Comets can be gravitationally ejected from the solar system
流放至太空
and exiled into space.
無論如何
And yet, somehow,
彗星總會回來
the comets keep coming.
奧爾特和其他天文學家自忖
Oort and other astronomers wondered,
這些彗星都是哪裏來的
"Where do all the comets come from?"
奧爾特通過計算新彗星出現的比率
Oort calculated the rate at which new comets appear
得出結論
and concluded that there must be
由數量極多的彗星組成一個
a vast, spherical swarm of them,
直徑達到幾光年的
a few light-years across,
園球狀包圍太陽
surrounding the Sun.
奧爾特的理論時至今日依然成立
Oort's logic still holds up,
哪怕是幾十年後  我們對彗星和太陽系
even after all the discoveries we've made about comets
有了更多的認識的今天
and the solar system in the many decades since.
不過  奧爾特雲團是個
And yet, the Oort Cloud is a sight
無人能看到的景象
that no one has ever seen.
我們也不行
Nor could we.
那裏漆黑一片
It's dark out here.
最近的兩個彗星間的距離就如同
And each comet is about as far from its closest neighbor
地球到土星的距離
as the Earth is from Saturn.
但是 科學給我們特殊的能力
But science gives us special powers of our own.
科學給了奧爾特
It gave Jan Oort
預見的天賦
the gift of prophecy.
奧爾特也是第一個正確估計出
Oort was also the first to correctly estimate
太陽到銀河系中心的距離
the distance between the Sun and the center of our galaxy.
這是很了不起的成就
That's a big deal--
找到了我們在銀河系的位置
finding out where we are in the Milky Way.
我們的恆星
Our star is about
距離中心3萬光年
30,000 light-years from the center.
奧爾特也是首個
Oort was also
使用射電望遠鏡
the first guy to use a radio telescope
繪製出了銀河系的螺旋結構
to map the galaxy's spiral structure.
並且 他發現銀河系的中心
And he discovered that the center of our galaxy
發生著一連串極大的爆炸
was a place of titanic explosions,
這是第一個跡象 顯示出那裏可能
the first indication that there might have been
暗藏著一個巨大的黑洞
a supermassive black hole lurking there.
事實上 我們中的很多人
Does the fact that most of us know
知道著名殺人魔的名字
the names of mass murderers,
卻從沒聽說過奧爾特
but never heard of Jan Oort,
人性就是如此
say anything about us?
奧爾特雲團是如此巨大
The Oort Cloud is so enormous
彗星要用100萬年
that it takes one of its comets about a million years
才能繞太陽一圈
to complete a single trip around the Sun.
在這裏 太陽系的邊緣
Out here, at the far edge of the solar system,
即使擦肩而過的星星產生的輕微引力
even a little tug from the gravity of a passing star
也會使這些彗星
can liberate some of these comets
擺脫太陽引力的束縛
from their gravitational bondage to the Sun.
一些彗星被拋出太陽系
Some comets are flung out of the solar system
從此在星際空間遊蕩
to wander interstellar space.
其他的一些彗星 卻有著不同的命運
But for others, there's a different fate.
這顆彗星被拋向太陽
This one is plunging towards the Sun,
在無阻力的自由落體中不斷加速
gaining speed in an unbroken free fall
一直持續幾十萬年
that lasts hundreds of thousands of years.
當海王星的引力再次吸引它時
When Neptune's gravity gives it another tug,
它的軌跡發生了小小的變化
there's a small change in course.
強大的木星
Mighty Jupiter, the most massive
太陽系中質量最大的物體
object in our solar system--
除太陽以外
other than the Sun-- attracts the comet
用它強大的引力再次改變彗星的軌跡
with its powerful gravitational pull, bending its path.
當這顆彗星到達太陽系的核心
When our comet reaches the inner solar system...
太陽的熱量烘烤著它
heat from the Sun bakes it.
一場美麗的轉變開始了
A beautiful transformation begins.
被煙燻黑的貧瘠冰山
The barren, sooty iceberg
變幻出灼熱的光暈
now sports a glowing halo...
還有彗尾
and a tail.
這些粉塵層描述著大約40億年前
These layers tell the story of how the comet was made,
彗星產生的過程
some four billion years ago.
在4萬代人的歷史中
During the 40,000 generations of humanity,
至少有大約10萬次
there must have been roughly 100,000 apparitions
耀眼的彗星劃過天際
of a bright comet.
那個時候
For all that time,
我們只能仰望  不禁的驚嘆
the best we could do was look up in helpless wonder,
無助的人們不知所措
prisoners of Earth with nowhere to turn
除了恐懼和悔恨 沒有更好的辦法
for an explanation beyond our guilt and our fears.
後來 兩個人的友情為人類的思想
But then a friendship began between two men that led
帶來了翻天覆地的革命
to a permanent revolution in human thought.
艾薩克·牛頓和愛德蒙·哈雷 也是始料未及
Isaac Newton and Edmond Halley could not know it,
他們的研究成果將我們從
but their collaboration would ultimately set us free
這顆小星球的局限中徹底解放
from our long confinement on this tiny world.
1664年的這顆彗星
The Comet of 1664
令整個歐洲恐懼顫慄
sent shivers of dread throughout Europe,
隨後發生的大瘟疫和倫敦大火災
and the terror seemed justified when the Plague
恰巧印證了人們的恐懼
and the Great Fire of London followed soon after.
那血色的長髮
There, with long bloody hair,
耀眼的星辰威脅整個世界
a blazing star threatens the world
帶來饑荒  瘟疫 戰爭
with famine, plague and war.
王子們的死亡
To princes, it spells death...
王國多了無數的墓碑
to kingdoms, many crosses...
不可避免的財產損失
to all estates, inevitable losses...
腐爛的牧群
to herdsmen, rot,
顆粒無收的莊稼漢
to plowmen, hapless seasons,
海上的風暴
to sailors, it brings storms,
暴動的市民
to cities, civil treasons.
但有一個孩子
But for one child,
並不覺得彗星有那麼恐怖
the comet was not the least bit frightening.
對他來說 只是驚奇
For him, it was a thing of wonder.
和我們一樣  愛德蒙·哈雷生性好奇
Like all of us, Edmond Halley was born curious.
哇塞
Hell's bells!
他很幸運  他的父親支持並鼓勵他的求知慾
He was lucky to have a father who encouraged and nurtured his curiosity,
給他買了最好的科學儀器
buying him the best scientific instruments
資助他的探險考察
and even funding his expedition
為了畫出第一張精確的南半球星空圖
to make the first accurate star map of the Southern Hemisphere.
哈雷20歲時從牛津輟學
Halley dropped out of Oxford when he was 20,
去了聖赫勒拿島
and sailed to St. Helena,
一個位於赤道以南  非洲的西海岸的小島
an island below the equator, off the west coast of Africa.
哇塞
Hell's bells.
問題是 沒人告訴哈雷
The problem was, nobody told Halley
島上的天氣狀況是如此糟糕
that the weather on St. Helena was generally lousy;
他用了12個月
it took him 12 frustrating months
才觀測到足夠的南半球星星來繪製完整的星圖
to observe enough southern stars to make a complete map.
古希臘的眾神和英雄人物
The gods and heroes of ancient Greece were now joined
由虛構的圖形將他們匯聚在一起
by the mythic figures of a new world and age,
巨喙鳥  指南針  天堂鳥
a toucan, a compass, a bird of paradise.
當哈雷帶著《南天星表》回到家時
When Halley came home with the other half of the sky,
他的星空圖造成了轟動
his map created a sensation.
商人和探險家可以根據隨處可見的星星導航
Now merchants and explorers could navigate by the stars visible anywhere on Earth.
當時 倫敦的皇家學會
At the time, the World Society of London
是世界上科學發現的集散地
was the world's clearinghouse of scientific discovery.
它的格言是 不人云亦云
Its motto, "Nullius in verba,"
總結出了科學方法的中心思想
sums up the heart of the scientific method.
它是拉丁語中的 親自求證
It's Latin for "see for yourself."
換言之 質疑權威
In other words, "question authority."
哈雷的星圖引起了學會實驗室負責人的注意
Halley's star maps caught the attention of the Society's Curator of Experiments.
我也想讓你看看他的樣子
I'd show him to you if I could,
但羅伯特·胡克並沒有留下任何的肖像畫
but no portrait of Robert Hooke exists from his time,
只有他的事跡口耳相傳
only the verbal descriptions of his contemporaries.
他們說他 瘦弱 駝背 醜陋
They called him "lean, bent, ugly."
他可能是最有創造性的天才
He was possibly the most inventive person who ever lived.
不論他的外表如何
And despite his appearance,
他在當時的倫敦炙手可熱
he was the most sought-after party guest in all of London.
為何
Why?
因為胡克永不滿足的求知慾
Hooke's insatiable curiosity
覆蓋了所有的領域
encompassed absolutely everything.
胡克發現了一個小宇宙
Hooke discovered a little cosmos,
我們至今沿用他給它的命名  細胞
and we still call it by the name he gave it, the cell.
單詞原意：單人房
胡可通過觀察一片軟木片發現了細胞
Hooke discovered the cell by looking
正是用了他自己的一項發明
at a piece of cork with one of his own inventions,
復合顯微鏡
the compound microscope.
他提出的觀點比達爾文的進化論
He anticipated aspects of Darwin's theory of evolution
早了幾乎200年
by almost 200 years.
胡克又改良瞭望遠鏡
Hooke also improved the telescope.
他根據觀察天體所做的素描
The drawings he made of the astronomical bodies he observed
見證了他異乎尋常的準確性
attest to his uncanny precision.
1666年的倫敦大火災摧毀了倫敦中部
After the Great Fire destroyed central London in 1666,
胡克與建築師 克裏斯多佛·雷恩合作
Hooke partnered with the architect Christopher Wren
重新設計 建設 倫敦
to redesign and rebuild the city.
胡克是當時首屈一指的實驗主義者
Hooke was the foremost experimentalist of his age.
使用彈簧
Using coiled springs,
他提出了 彈性定律
he derived the "law of elasticity,"
我們稱之為  胡克定律
known today as Hooke's Law.
他改良了氣泵
He perfected the air pump,
達到了當時的技術頂峰
the height of technology in its time,
並將之用於聲音和呼吸實驗
and used it to experiment on respiration and sound.
他用大麻做實驗
And he experimented with cannabis.
他在一次皇家學會的會議上報告
He reported to a meeting of the Royal Society
據他的一位船長朋友說
that a sea captain friend of his
「經常食用這個東西
"had so often experimented with it,
不會令人產生恐懼
that there is no cause of fear,
只會帶來喜悅」
though possibly there may be of laughter."
咖啡在17世紀的英格蘭
But coffee was the drug of choice for England
是最受歡迎的
in the 17th century.
咖啡館遍佈倫敦
Coffeehouses sprang up all over London.
人們在那裏獲取新聞
This is where people came to get news,
發表新的觀點 討論時事
to launch new ventures, and to debate ideas.
咖啡館是這個注重階級的社會中
The coffeehouse was an oasis of equality
平等的綠洲
in a class-obsessed society.
在這裏  窮人不需要給富人讓座
Here, a poor man needn't give up his seat
也不用屈從他的觀點
to a rich man, nor submit to his opinion.
就像是民主制度的實驗室
It was a kind of laboratory of democracy.
在這種高度興奮刺激的氣氛中
In this highly caffeinated atmosphere,
哈雷和胡克 與克裏斯多佛·雷恩討論著一個謎團
Halley and Hooke met Christopher Wren to discuss a deep mystery.
為何行星如此運動
Why do the planets move as they do?
天文學家約翰內斯·開普勒在此前的
The astronomer Johannes Kepler had demonstrated,
80多年 就證明了
some 80 years before,
行星繞太陽公轉的軌道
that the orbits of the planets around the Sun
並不是正圓  而是橢圓形
were not perfect circles, but actually ellipses,
行星越靠近太陽
and that the closer a planet was to the Sun,
運動的越快
the faster it moved.
為什麼
Why?
會是太陽發出某些看不見的力量 導致這種變化嗎
Could some invisible force from the Sun be responsible for this change in motion?
如果是  又是如何導致的呢
If so, how did it work?
可以用一個簡單的數學定律描述嗎
Could there be a simple mathematical law to describe it?
就像胡克的彈性定律那樣
Maybe something like Hooke's Law of Elasticity?
有可能
Perhaps.
但是 嘗試之後
But try as he might,
克裏斯多佛·雷恩沒有答案
Christopher Wren couldn't figure it out.
總好過沒有嘗試過
Damned if I haven't tried.
我的能力有限
It's beyond me.
我押上這本價值40先令的書
I'll wager a book worth 40 shillings
誰能解決 誰就拿去
to the man who can solve it!
我拿定了  雷恩先生
That book is mine, Mr. Wren.
我已經完成了計算
I've already done the calculation.
哈雷非常開心
Halley was delighted.
快讓我們見識見識  胡克先生
Show us, Mr. Hooke.
但幾個月過去  胡克也沒能做到
But months passed, and Hooke failed to deliver.
他算不過來
He couldn't do the math.
沒人能夠
None of them could.
最後 哈雷厭煩了胡克的借口
Finally, Halley had enough of Hooke's excuses.
哈雷知道 肯定在某個地方 有某個人
Halley knew there must be someone, somewhere,
可以做到
up to the challenge.
劍橋大學的數學家怎麼樣
What about that mathematician at Cambridge?
聰明的傢伙
Clever fellow.
他多年前就解決了光線本質的核心問題
He had solved central questions about the nature of light
他當時只有22歲
years before, when he was still only 22.
他發明了反射望遠鏡
And he invented the reflecting telescope.
怪人
Odd bird.
銷聲匿跡過一段時間
Dropped out of sight a while back;
對胡克本人和他的光學理論有些不同看法
some squabble over Hooke and his discovery about light.
走了極端  無法自拔
Went completely to pieces over it
從此在劍橋大學隱居
and has been hiding out in Cambridge ever since.
哈雷很期待 這個怪人
Halley wondered if this strange, and by all accounts,
據說 很難相處的人
exceedingly difficult man, might succeed
是否能成功
where Hooke and others had failed.
他當時並不知道
What he couldn't know,
沒有任何人會想到
what no one could possibly imagine at the time,
整個世界
were the countless ways
就在1684年8月的某一天
the world would be forever changed by this meeting
各個方面都因為這次見面 從此改變
on an August day in 1684.
艾薩克·牛頓出生於英格蘭
Isaac Newton was born in England
1642年的聖誕節
on Christmas Day in 1642.
父親在他出生前就過世了
Before he even opened his eyes, his father was already dead.
3歲時 母親也拋棄了他
His mother left him when he was only three
直到11歲才再次見面
and did not return until he was 11.
她已經有了新的家庭
When she did, it was with a new family and husband,
牛頓鄙視他的繼父
a stepfather who Isaac Newton despised.
悲慘家庭環境中的唯一避風港
Newton's refuge from his miserable family life
就是牛頓對於科學研究的熱情
was his passion to understand how things worked,
特別是自然科學
especially nature itself.
1661年  天資聰穎的艾薩克進了劍橋大學三一學院
In 1661, the talented young Isaac entered Trinity College at Cambridge University
他在學校很不合群
where he was a consistently lousy student,
沒有家人和朋友
one without friends or a loving family
給他絲毫的溫暖和鼓勵
to provide any warmth or encouragement.
牛頓不與人交流  把自己關在房間裏
Newton mostly kept to himself, sequestered in his room,
學習古希臘的哲學
studying ancient Greek philosophers,
幾何和語言
geometry and languages,
琢磨著更深層次的問題
and pondering deep questions
關於自然  空間  時間  運動
on the nature of matter, space, time, and motion.
這位才華初露的科學家也是一名狂熱的神秘主義者
This budding scientist was also a passionate mystic.
牛頓相信這種只為小部分
Newton believed that a secret knowledge
古代哲學家所知的煉金術
called alchemy, known only to a small group of ancient philosophers,
正等著他去重新發現
was waiting to be rediscovered.
他希望可以學會把普通金屬
He hoped to learn how to change ordinary metals
變成金銀的方法
into silver and gold,
或許可以做出生命合劑
and maybe even cook up the elixir of life,
以此長生不老
the key to to immortality.
他一心想從聖經的字裏行間
He was also obsessed
找到隱藏的信息
with finding hidden messages in the words of the Bible.
他梳理了不用語言的譯本
He combed through translations in several different languages,
試圖破譯加密了的上帝的指示
hoping to decipher coded instructions from God.
他做了詳盡的計算
He made elaborate calculations in an effort
只為發現基督再次降臨的日期
to discover the date of the Second Coming.
窮其一生研究煉金術
His lifelong research in alchemy
研究聖經  可惜沒有任何突破
and biblical chronology never led anywhere.
當哈雷找到牛頓的那天
When Halley found Newton that fateful day,
牛頓一直過著隱居的生活
he was living as a virtual recluse.
牛頓自從羅伯特·胡克公開指責他
Newton had gone into hiding 13 years earlier,
剽竊胡克關於光學和顏色的突破性成果
after Robert Hooke had publicly accused Newton of stealing
已經隱居了13年
his groundbreaking work on light and color.
事實上 牛頓才是那個
In fact, it was Isaac Newton
解開光譜謎團的人
who solved the mystery of the spectrum of light,
並不是羅伯特·胡克
not Robert Hooke.
這對他的打擊很大
This wound was painful and deep,
牛頓下定決心從此再不讓自己陷入
and Newton resolved to never expose himself to that kind
那種被人羞辱的境地
of public humiliation ever again.
先生 你可能不記得了
Sir, I don't suppose you recall
我們幾年前見過
our meeting a few years ago?
我記得 哈雷先生
Yes, Mr. Halley.
抱歉來打攪你
I'm sorry to bother you.
不用客套 有話直說
Never mind the formalities, get to your point.
我一直與我們的朋友  胡克和雷恩在討論
I've been talking with our friends, Mr. Wren and Mr. Hooke.
胡克那個人渣不是我的朋友
That scoundrel Hooke's no friend of mine.
我明白
Yes, I understand, sir.
重點是 我們一直在討論
But the thing is we've been debating
行星運動的難題
the puzzling question of planetary motion.
我們都認同 某種吸引的力量
We all agree that some force of attraction
來自太陽  控制著行星的運動
from the Sun governs the motions of the planets.
我們感覺一定能有一條數學定律
We suspect there must be a mathematical law
來形容這種
to describe how this force
根據距離而改變的力量
changes with distance.
以您的能力
And knowing of your skill...
沒錯 重力所產生的吸引力
Yes, yes, the attraction of gravity
與距離的平方成反比
weakens with the square of the distance.
這就是橢圓軌道的原因
That's why the planets move in ellipses.
但您是怎麼知道的
But, sir, how can you know this?
怎麼了 我5年多前就算出來了
Why, I have calculated it some five years ago.
求你了 讓我見識一下
I beg you, show it to me.
計算的結果在這裏
The calculation is here...
就在周圍
somewhere.
沒關係
Well, no matter.
我重新做一份
I shall redo it and be sure
然後寄給你
to send it on to you.
太不可思議了
This is stupendous!
相見恨晚啊
Why have we not had word of it before?
牛頓還記得上次
Newton remembered all too well
他提出新的理論時
what Hooke had done to him
胡克的所作所為
the last time he put forth an idea.
就在哈雷開始懷疑
Just when Halley may have begun to wonder
牛頓是否也像胡克那樣吹牛時
if Newton was bluffing as Hooke had done earlier,
信使帶來牛頓的一封信
a messenger arrived with an envelope from Newton.
這是現代科學理論的開篇
Here are the opening pages of modern science
包含了對於大自然的洞察
with its all-embracing vision of nature...
運動定律  萬有引力
universal laws of motion, gravity...
不單適用於地球
not just for the Earth,
也適用於整個宇宙
but for the cosmos.
哈雷迫不及待地回到劍橋
Halley raced back to Cambridge.
牛頓大人  我求你趕緊
Mr. Newton, I beseech you to work all of this
把這些都寫進你的書裏吧
into a book as soon as possible.
我向你保證 皇家學一定會出版你的書
I can assure you the Royal Society will publish it.
但還有一個小問題
But there was one little problem.
我們同意
We are in agreement
牛頓先生的成果是偉大的
that Mr. Newton has produced a masterpiece.
但是  皇家學會恐怕
However, I'm afraid the Royal Society has...
因為《魚類歷史》的慘淡銷售
well, regrettably sales for the History of Fish...
造成我們的財政狀況並不樂觀
have not lived up to our financial expectations.
這是一本很棒的書
It's an impressive book.
包羅萬象
Extremely comprehensive.
真的
Really.
使用了大量的插圖來描述
It's filled with lavish illustrations of...
魚類
well, fish.
銷量慘淡帶來更大的問題
The disappointing sales led to a bigger problem.
就是皇家學會在出版《魚類歷史》上
The Royal Society pretty much blew
幾乎花了整年的預算
its total annual budget on the History of Fish.
他們現金短缺
In fact, they were so strapped for cash,
他們不得不用那賣不掉的書
they had to pay poor Halley's salary
來抵本應支付給哈雷的工資
with copies of their worst-selling book.
沒有錢來印刷牛頓的《原理》
With no money to print Newton's Principia,
科學革命 命懸一線
the scientific revolution hung in the balance.
要不是哈雷的努力
Without Halley's heroic efforts,
牛頓的這部巨著
the reclusive Newton's masterwork
可能永無出頭之日
might never have seen the light of day.
哈雷的堅持不懈
But Halley was a man on a mission,
將牛頓的天才展現給了全世界
absolutely determined to bring Newton's genius to the world.
那個科學革命以前
That pre-scientific world,
靠恐懼來統治的世界
the world ruled by fear,
已經被推向了革命的邊緣
was poised at the edge of a revolution.
一切就看愛德蒙·哈雷能否
Everything depended on whether or not Edmond Halley
將牛頓的新書推向世界
could get Newton's book out to the wider world.
哈雷編輯並且出版了牛頓的書
Halley resolved not only to edit Newton's book,
全都自掏腰包
but to publish it at his own expense.
在牛頓完成的頭兩卷裏
Newton completed the first two volumes,
用數學公式
laying the mathematical framework
來描述物理運動
for the physics of motion.
第三卷徹底決定了誰才是咖啡館的
The third volume would settle once and for all
賭局贏家
who won the coffeehouse wager.
牛頓運用他的原理可以解釋
Newton applied his principles to explain
地球上所有的運動
all the known motions of the Earth,
月亮和其他行星
the Moon and the planets.
不幸的是 還有一個問題
Unfortunately, there was this problem.
哈雷又變成了
Now Halley also took on the role
牛頓的心理醫生
of Newton's psychotherapist.
艾薩克  那個  胡克先生要求
Isaac, I'm afraid that Mr. Hooke requires
在你的第三卷序言裏向他致謝
an acknowledgment in the preface of your third volume.
我已經做過了啊
But I have done so.
謝謝他 雷恩先生還有你
Thanking him, Mr. Wren and yourself
激勵我重新思考有關天文學的事情
for prodding me to think again on astronomical matters.
胡克在倫敦到處說
Mr. Hooke has been going about London saying
你的萬有引力定律是借鑒了他
that you got the Law of Gravity from him.
我要告他這個小...
Why, that litigious little...
做夢
Never!
我寧可燒了我的第三卷
I would sooner burn the third volume
也不會讓這種謊言玷污它
than deface it with such a lie.
讓胡克去死吧
To hell with Hooke.
他會被人們遺忘
He will be long forgotten
而你的理論會被人們永遠歌頌
when your ideas are still being celebrated.
又是這些噁心的書
More copies of that dreadful book?
家裏都快放不下了
Wherever shall we put them all?
我和你說過的 瑪麗 親愛的
We talked about this, Mary, dear.
這是科學院給我的薪水
This is my salary from the Society.
他們也拿不出其他東西了
They have nothing else with which to pay me.
如果胡克和牛頓也能像你這樣就好了
If only Mr. Hooke and Mr. Newton were more like you.
哈雷和雷恩決定和胡克對質
Halley and Wren decided to confront Hooke
關於他不實的言論
about his false claims.
那是我的定律 我告訴你
That law is mine, I tell you!
我先證明的
I proved it first.
那就把你的證據拿出來
Then fetch your proof here at once.
讓我們看看
Let us see it.
反正我們都等了這麼久了
Surely we have waited on it long enough.
你只要相信我的話就可以了
You'll simply have to take my word for it.
空口無憑或許在其他地方行得通
Empty claims may persuade elsewhere,
但這裏不行
but not here.
"勿輕信人言"
拿不出來就閉嘴  胡克先生
Put up or shut up, Mr. Hooke.
牛頓這個混蛋  我要他付出代價
Blasted Newton. I'll make him pay.
"自然哲學的數學原理"
如果沒有愛德蒙·哈雷
If it wasn't for Edmond Halley,
牛頓絕沒有機會構思
Newton's great book would've never been conceived,
書寫 出版他的書
nor written, nor printed.
好吧  那又怎樣
Okay. So what?
對我們來說有什麼不一樣
What difference does that make to us?
有什麼大不了的
What's the big deal?
當牛頓在這棟房子裏誕生時
When Isaac Newton was born in this house
1642年  那是的世界和現在完全不一樣
in 1642, the world was very different.
每個人看到天空中的眾多星星
Everyone looked at the perfection
像鐘錶一樣極有規律的準確運行
of the clockwork motions of the planets in the sky
只能想到的是出自
and could only understand it as the work
一個偉大的「鐘錶匠」
of a master clock maker.
還能怎麼解釋
How else to explain it?
他們只能想出一種解釋
There was only one way such a thing could come about
以他們的想像力
in their imagination;
只有一種答案
only one answer for them--
上帝
God.
出於我們還不瞭解的原因
For reasons beyond our understanding,
上帝就是這麼創造的太陽系
God just created the solar system that way.
這個解釋卻是一個死結
But this explanation is the closing of a door.
並無法解釋其他的問題
It doesn't lead to other questions.
牛頓來了
Along came Newton,
上帝寵愛的人  大天才
a God-loving man who's also a genius.
他能用完美的數學語句
He could write the laws of nature
寫出大自然的定律
in perfect mathematical sentences--
對宇宙有效的方程式
formulas that applied universally
對蘋果 月亮 行星都有效
to apples, moons, planets
還有很多
and so much more.
雖然仍身處中世紀
With one foot still in the Middle Ages,
牛頓已經想像出了整個太陽系
Isaac Newton imagined the whole solar system.
牛頓的萬有引力和運動定律
Newton's laws of gravity and motion
揭示了太陽如何維繫這些遙遠的星球
revealed how the Sun held distant worlds captive.
他的定律使人們不再需要
His laws swept away the need
用「鐘錶匠」來解釋
for a master clock maker
為什麼太陽系能如此精準的運行
to explain the precision and beauty of the solar system.
萬有引力就是鐘錶匠
Gravity is the clock maker.
事物遵循我們發現的戒律運動
Matter obeyed commandments we could discover,
遵循聖經沒有提到過的定律運動
laws the Bible hadn't mentioned.
牛頓的理論解釋了為什麼太陽子會是這樣的
Newton's answer to why the solar system is the way it is
也為其他無數的問題打開了大門
opened the way to an infinite number of questions.
《原理》的內容裏包括
Principia also happened to include
微積分的發明
the invention of calculus,
還有第一個堅實的理論基礎
and the first sound theoretical basis
為我們打破了地球的枷鎖
for an end to our imprisonment on Earth--
太空旅行
space travel.
牛頓設想 發射出去的炮彈
Newton envisioned the firing of a cannonball...
隨著爆炸推力的增加
with increasingly greater explosive thrust.
只要速度足夠快
He reasoned that with enough velocity,
就可以突破引力的界限
the bounds of gravity could be broken,
炮彈就可以離開地球
and the cannonball could escape
繞地球旋轉
to orbit the Earth.
這 改變了 整個世界
This changed everything.
牛頓的數學原理 將我們徹底解放
Newton's Principia Mathematica set us free in another way.
通過找到控制彗星運行的自然定律
By finding the natural laws governing the comings and goings of comets,
他使我們不再像祖先那樣
he decoupled the motions of the heavens
恐懼天體運行
from their ancient connections to our fears.
如果哈雷沒有竭盡全力的支持牛頓
If Halley hadn't been standing next to Newton for all those years,
人們可能會記住他自己的發現和成就
perhaps the world would remember him for his own accomplishments and discoveries.
而不是 僅僅記住一個彗星的名字
But the only thing that comes to mind for most people
諷刺的是  發現彗星這件事
is the comet, the irony is that discovering a comet
其實哈雷從沒有做過
is actually one of the few things that Halley never did.
有冰山
Mountain of ice to starboard
左滿舵
Come about
報告哈雷隊長
Aye, aye, Captain Halley!
《原理》出版後
After the publication of the Principia
哈雷奉命帶領3艘大船  出海科學考察
Halley was commanded by his king to lead three ocean voyages,
為英國海軍解決導航的問題
scientific expeditions to solve navigational problems for the British navy.
哈雷利用這次機會  繪製了第一張地球磁場圖
Halley used this opportunity to make the first map of the Earth's magnetic field
他同時也是個商人
And he was also a businessman.
哈雷改良了潛水鐘
Halley perfected the diving bell...
並用他的發明
...and used his invention to start
開創了繁榮的商業打撈業務
a flourishing commercial salvage operation.
嗯 哈雷博士這次是真的做到了
Mmm, ah, Dr. Halley's gone and done it this time.
我看他在下面最少3個小時了
I reckon he's been down there at least three hours.
沒人拿其他人的生命冒險
Not one to risk the lives of others,
哈雷親自測試他的發明
Halley personally tested his own invention.
下來以後已經堅持了4個小時
I make it exactly four hours since our descent.
對10英尋的深度來說不錯了
Not at all bad for ten fathoms.
10英尋等於約18米
他發明了氣象圖
He invented the weather map.
他設計的標示盛行風的符號
And the symbols he devised for indicating prevailing winds
一直沿用至今
are still in use today.
星期一天氣預測
世界天氣
哈雷為人口統計學
Halley laid the groundwork
打下了堅實的基礎
for the science of population statistics.
怎麼做的
How?
他對比倫敦和巴黎的出生 結婚 死亡人數
He compared the birth, marriage, death,
以及人口密度
and population densities of London and Paris.
他真的用雙腳
He actually had to pace off
測量出巴黎的周長
the entire perimeter of Paris, on foot,
只為計算正確的面積
to learn its true dimensions.
他總結出
He came to the conclusion
既然大約一半的成年人
that since roughly half of all adults fail
無法生孩子
to reproduce children,
要延續他們繁衍的基因
who themselves survive to reproduce,
每對夫妻必須要有4個孩子
every married couple must have four children
才能保持人口數量
in order to maintain the population.
愛德蒙 哈雷告訴我們
And it was Edmond Halley who gave us
太陽系的實際比例
the actual scale of the solar system.
他找到一個聰明的辦法算出
He figured out a clever way to find the distance
地球到太陽的距離
from Earth to the Sun.
通過精確地測量
It involved precisely measuring the time it took
金星穿過日面所用的時間
for the planet Venus to cross the Sun's disc.
即金星凌日
哈雷過世後的27年
27 years after Halley's death,
詹姆士庫克船長第一次到達塔希提島
Captain James Cook made his first voyage to Tahiti
為了驗證哈雷的方法
for the express purpose of testing Halley's method
在觀察在金星凌日的過程中
during a transit of Venus across the Sun.
他用一種特殊的濾鏡保護眼睛
Using a special filter to protect his vision
防止直視太陽帶來的損傷
from being destroyed by looking directly at the Sun,
庫克團隊的努力使我們知道
Cook and his men made it possible for us to know
約為1.5億公里
太陽距離地球9300萬英里
that the Sun is 93 million miles from Earth.
哈雷也是第一個認識到
And Halley was the first to realize
所謂的恆星 並非靜止不動
that the so-called "fixed" stars were not fixed at all.
他是怎麼知道的
How'd he do it?
他將古希臘天文學家
He pored over the observations made
對最明亮的星星的觀測結果
by the ancient Greek astronomers of the brightest stars.
與他在1800年後觀測的同一顆星星的
And he compared their observations with the ones
觀測結果作比較
he himself made of the same stars 1,800 years later.
為什麼之前沒人注意到
Why hadn't anyone noticed this before?
哈雷意識到要想觀察出來
Halley figured out that it would only become apparent
兩次的觀測時間要間隔很長才行
if you waited long enough between observations.
要觀察到相距遙遠的物體間的移動
It's hard to perceive the motions of things
是很困難的
that are far away.
而且恆星間的距離是如此的遙遠
And the stars are so very far away,
要花幾百年的時間去觀察
that you would need to track them for many centuries
才能察覺他們的移動
before you could detect that they moved at all.
哈雷發現了一個宏偉的現實
Halley discovered the first clue to a magnificent reality,
所有的恆星都在運動 相互趕超
all the stars are in motion, streaming past each other,
和旋轉木馬一樣上升和降落
rising and falling like merry-go-round horses
在銀河系中此起彼伏
in their Newtonian dance around the center of our galaxy.
對了 還有彗星的事情
And, oh, yes, there was that thing about the comet.
這些美麗的陌生天外訪客到底是誰
What were those strange and beautiful celestial visitors
時不時的突然造訪
that appeared without warning from time to time?
哈雷用偵探常用的方法來解決這個謎團
Halley set out to solve this mystery as a detective would,
搜集所有可靠目擊證人的證詞
by gathering all credible eyewitness testimony.
哈雷能找到的最早準確觀察到
The earliest precise observations of a comet
彗星的證人是位於君士坦丁堡的
that Halley could find were made in Constantinople
尼斯波羅斯·貴格列 拜占庭帝國的天文學家兼僧人
by Nikephoros Gregoras, a Byzantine astronomer and monk
1337年6月
in June 1337.
哈雷收集了1472-1698年間所有的
Halley hunted down every astronomical observation
在歐洲的彗星觀測記錄
of a comet recorded in Europe between 1472 and 1698.
請記住 那時還沒有
And remember, there was no such thing
搜索引擎 或者電腦
as a search engine or a computer.
哈雷只能依靠他的書和大腦
All Halley had were his books and his mind.
困難的地方到了
Now here comes the hard part,
哈雷必須要按照每個彗星的觀察結果
Halley had to take the observations made for each comet
在太空中的找出實際的運動軌跡
and find the shape of its actual path through space.
除了牛頓 沒人嘗試過
No one else but Newton had yet attempted
將他的定律應用於天文學的問題
to apply his new set of laws to an astronomical question.
這是一次艱巨的數學運算的壯舉
In an arduous tour de force of mathematical brilliance,
哈雷發現彗星被太陽束縛在
Halley discovered that comets were bound to the Sun
長橢圓的軌道上
in long elliptical orbits.
他是第一個知道1531年發現的那個彗星
And he was the first to know that the comets seen in 1531,
和1607年 還有1682年發現的
1607, and 1682...
是同一顆彗星
were one and the same--
每隔76年回歸一次
a single comet that returned every 76 years.
這是識別規律的絕佳例子
In a stunning example of true pattern recognition,
他預測彗星還會回歸
he predicted it would be seen again
在超過50年後的未來
more than 50 years in the future.
上千年來 彗星都很神秘
For millennia, comets had been props for mystics,
被巫師們視為人類事件的預兆
who considered them to be merely omens of human events.
哈雷打破了他們的壟斷
Halley shattered their monopoly,
以他們熟悉的領域裏
beating them at their own game,
以前沒有科學家進入過的領域
a game that no scientist had ever played before...
預言
prophecy.
他沒有閃爍其詞
And he did not hedge his bet.
就像貝比·魯斯預測
Like Babe Ruth predicting
他的下一個全壘打會落在哪裏
where his next home run would land in the stands,
哈雷明確地指出這顆彗星
Halley stated flatly that the comet would return
會在1758年底 出現在天空中的一個特定位置
at the end of 1758, from a particular part of the sky,
遵循一條特定的軌跡
following a specific path.
幾乎沒有一個由巫師提出的預言
There is hardly a prophecy attempted by the mystics
能和他的準確性相提並論
that ever even strives for comparable precision.
這就是 哈雷彗星
That's Halley's Comet.
漂浮在太陽系的邊緣
Out here at the edge of the solar system,
看上去並不大
it doesn't look like much.
只是太空中一塊冰石
Just a big hunk of ice and rock in space.
因為在海王星的軌道以外
That's because beyond the orbit of Neptune,
距離太陽大約50億公里
nearly five billion kilometers from the Sun,
彗星過得非常寧靜
comets lead very quiet lives.
因為到達了軌道的遠端
As it reaches the far end of its orbit,
它會慢下來 直到太陽將它拉回來
it'll slow down till the Sun allows it to go no farther.
然後它向太陽系的核心墜落
Then it will begin its long fall back to the inner solar system.
哈雷彗星繞著太陽做自由落體
Halley's comet is in free fall around the Sun.
太陽系中的一切  地球  月亮
Everything in our solar system-- the Earth, the Moon,
其他行星  彗星  小行星
the other planets, comets, asteroids,
都繞著太陽自由落體
all of them are falling around the Sun.
萬有引力將他們拉向太陽
Gravity pulls the planets towards the Sun,
但因為他們的軌道動量
but because of their orbital momentum,
他們保持環繞太陽  而不衝向太陽
they keep moving around the Sun, never falling into it.
羅伯特·胡克很多年前過世了
Robert Hooke had died years before,
一些壞習慣傷害了他的健康
having ruined his health with some bad habits...
天天服用苦艾 鴉片 水銀
daily doses of wormwood, opium, mercury.
幾個月後  牛頓取代了他的職位
A few months later, Newton was elected to replace him
當選皇家學會的會長
as president of the Royal Society.
據說胡克的肖像
It is said that a portrait of Hooke
曾經掛在這裏
once hung on these walls.
哈雷達成了很多天文學的豐功偉績
Halley lived on to accomplish many more astonishing feats.
他堅持工作到最後一刻 享年85歲
He worked right up to his death at age 85.
他做的最後一件事是叫了一杯葡萄酒
His final act was to call for a glass of wine.
愉快的品下
He downed it with pleasure...
呼出最後一口氣
and breathed his last breath.
據信在這樣的一個夜裏
Some believe that it was on a night like this
艾薩克牛頓終於實施了他對
that Isaac Newton finally took his revenge
羅伯特胡克的報復
against Robert Hooke.
哈雷的預言並未被人遺忘
But Halley's prophecy was not forgotten.
50年後
50 years later,
就在預言回歸的時間
as the time of the predicted return approached,
全世界的天文學家都希望
the world's astronomers vied
第一個觀察到 哈雷的彗星
to be the first to catch sight of his comet.
他們沒有失望
They weren't disappointed.
從此以後 每隔76年都有一次觀測熱潮
It's been welcomed back every 76 years since.
當哈雷彗星回到我們的天空時
When Halley's Comet returns to our skies,
日光加熱它表面的冰
sunlight will warm up the ice on its surface,
再一次釋放出
once again setting loose
內部的灰塵和氣體
the dust and gases trapped within.
哈雷彗星的最近一次回歸
Halley's Comet most recently visited our neighborhood
是1986年
back in 1986.
如果你在2061年看到這個
And if you're seeing this in 2061,
你就知道 它回來了
then you'll know it's back.
願你看到眼前的這些
May you feel the wonder of all those
令人驚嘆的奇跡時
who came before you...
不再害怕
and none of the fear.
牛頓定律使愛德蒙哈雷可以預見
Newton's laws made it possible for Edmond Halley
50年後的未來
to see some 50 years into the future
預測一顆彗星的運動軌跡
and predict the behavior of a single comet.
科學家們一直使用這些定律
Scientists have been using these laws ever since,
打開通往月球之路
opening the way to the Moon
乃至整個太陽系
and even beyond our solar system.
搖籃中的嬰兒開始學習走路了
The baby in the basket is learning to walk...
開始瞭解宇宙
and to know the cosmos.
還有最後一個預言
Which brings me to one last prophecy.
僅僅依靠牛頓的萬有引力定律
Using nothing more than Newton's laws of gravitation,
天文學家可以很確定的預測
we astronomers can confidently predict
幾十億年後
that several billion years from now,
我們的星系  銀河系
our home galaxy, the Milky Way,
會與我們的鄰居 僊女座 交匯
will merge with our neighboring galaxy Andromeda.
因為恆星間的距離
Because the distances between the stars
相對他們的體積來說 是如此的遙遠
are so great compared to their sizes,
只會有很少數的星星發生碰撞
few if any stars in either galaxy will actually collide.
遙遠未來 依然存在的生命
Any life on the worlds of that far-off future
應該很安全  但是他們可以欣賞到
should be safe, but they would be treated to an amazing,
持續幾十億年的星光秀
billion-year-long light show...
幾千億顆星星的群舞
a dance of a half a trillion stars...
還有一位偉人與他的摯友共同譜寫的精彩樂章
to music first heard on one little world by a man who had but one true friend.
中文字幕 @SaltyEggPain
藍光版字幕製作  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息